[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software Brian Brazil is the
founder of robust perception a company
that helps scale and support users of
the open source Prometheus and
monitoring tool Brian has committed
heavily to the Prometheus project before
starting robust perception Brian worked
at Google Brian welcome to software
engineering radio enough not to be here
let's start off by just talking about
monitoring what is monitoring so I've
talked to lots of people over the last
year or so and different people have
very very different ideas of what
monitoring is for example I've had
people when I say system I do monitoring
thinking that I'm you know watching your
network traffic to see if you're
accessing Facebook and work which is
obviously not what we do and so I see
monitoring as kind of four things one is
a nursing you when there is a problem or
it is eventually a problem you know a
business level problem the second thing
is giving the information you need to be
able to debug that problem and deterring
is to do long term trending and making
business decisions like if you know your
cache hit rate is 90% and your change
will go to 95% then that means maybe we
can get rid of hardware or add new
hardware and the fourth one is just
general plumbing so for example if hard
drive fails at the end of the day you
have to send a human in to fix that
because the robots aren't good enough
yet so those defender for things I see
at monitoring in a computer space
awesome give me an example of something
that you monitored when you worked at
Google so I was primarily working in ads
at Google and so we were monitoring the
system like the number of queries coming
in per second the aeration latency as
well as more system details so like we
had tons and tons of stats right
absolutely and I want to use that as an
example later on but you we're talking
about Prometheus today and you've
claimed that prometheus is a
next-generation monitoring system could
you talk about how monitoring using
Prometheus would differ from a
monitoring tool of the previous
generation okay so if you're looking at
the previous generation you're going to
look at something like say Nagios or
something that Celsus derived our
promise from push to right of you so
Nagios works on the principle of per
machine checks so it's basically I run
this shell script it returns true or
false and based on that I send alert to
a human so this is fine when you have
you know five machines that you're
carefully caring for or intending and
feeding but when you're talking like the
current generation where people are
talking about service talking about
clouds with native you might have
hundreds of machines which are tiny and
which appear and disappear all the time
so you know the MER from the single
machine isn't really that useful and it
also might be the case you know one
machine is being a little slow that
doesn't necessarily mean the service as
a whole is having a problem because
you're still well within SLA so like the
canonical example I think where this
comes in is you're running some form of
web service and you have an SLA for
latency
let's say latency it has to be under a
second but if you are using something
like Nagios is extremely difficult using
just Nagios to a nurse on the fact that
your latency is over a second because
you can only look at each machine and
you have to cut data somehow and you
can't look at the overall service view
so what a lot of people end up doing is
alerting on CPU being high which
sometimes might indicate a problem but a
second is a deadlock for example and
it's also kind of lots of false
positives let's say flog rotate runs a
bit long whereas it Prometheus because
you're getting insight from the inside
you have all the applications you can
get that latency you can aggregate it up
correctly and say hey I'm currently
doing 880 milliseconds everything's fine
and if one server is a little slow as
long as you're under that second
everything's good and also because it's
meant for dynamic toute environments as
machines or a discerning Roubaix
auto-scaling or bob up from any case
will automatically pick that up and take
care of it
and you don't sighs when ideas have to
restart and updating thing every time
talk a little bit more about why the
move to cloud architecture changes how
we are doing monitoring well the sound
architecture and there's microservice as
well to some extent effective because
previously you'd have a few bare metal
machines and because you've only a
handful of them you can get away with
doing things well by hand as you move
into more dynamic environments and cloud
environments machines aren't radiating
anymore what you have more is some form
of computing substrate because you'll
say hey give me two CPUs a gig of ram
and a bit of disk and it lands somewhere
so there's no longer this tight binding
between the services and the instances
and the processes you're running and the
actual machines so you have to care a
lot more about where teams are I'll be
able to deal with that because you know
now we're talking about you know the my
sequel machine it is a machine which is
currently running one part of my sequel
service we were talking about monitoring
this monitoring also encompass the act
of responding to events or is it merely
the the processing of events and the
creation of metrics about those events
well that's one of those things as it
depends who you talk to because
personally I would say to monitoring
ends when it's sitting in something like
pagers you see and then you're on to
Incident Response other people would say
it's part of the system it probably
really boils down through your cultural
philosophy so for example if you have a
NOC and that's part of your control
system for keeping things running then
hardly be that's part of monitoring
whereas if you're taking an approach
where everything is more isolated based
and so on that's going to human we're
putting a lot of intelligent talk behind
things
it's kind of a separate incident
response sitting but it probably really
just matters in your personal opinion I
don't think just a bright-line answer or
not working in the past software
companies would often end up with a
variety of monitoring tools why did that
happen
so the thing is that those various tools
have been developed over time that just
do one ting particularly well or support
one integration particularly well and so
for example if you're going to
using say elasticsearch it has its own
ting for using Cassandra who have sax is
tool and each of those are integrated
and work well for just a two and then
you end up with all of those over time
handling different things so one of the
things - I think it's a niche about
prometheus is because we have all these
integrations that's great but every
other monitoring system out there also
has to implement those whether they're
commercial or open-source and that's
kind of annoying that we're all spending
your time reading formatting these
integrations rather than focusing on the
more interesting problems so one of the
things with Prometheus is that yes we
have water exporters and we also provide
the API is in the interfaces that you
can reuse them for other watering
systems so that other people you know
you don't have to duplicate as much
stuff right so is that duplication would
you say that's the main consequence of
the main negative consequence of so when
a software company has to run multiple
monitoring tools yeah it's one of these
duplications and then each of them tends
have a slightly different philosophy
slightly different data models and
different alerts rush shows different
levels of power and as with any system
or you have cordobas a build system or a
language or even a text editor if we're
going to start to the embrace Emacs Wars
for every single additional one of those
you have in your ecosystem that's more
cognitive load for all your team so it's
not so much to this monitoring it's just
yes one more ting everyone has to learn
and learn all the intricacies of and all
the special cases and all that sort of
thing
so if you're able to consolidate down so
that the size of the system people have
to understand is smaller that's better
for everyone as we get to talking about
prometheus prometheus is based on a
monitoring tool that was built inside of
Google called
orgmen what was unique about Borgman so
I don't know too much of the history of
Borglum and I just used it a lot and I
think
portman because if you look at
Prometheus it's just that it's meant for
dynamic environments it has labels cause
tags or dimensions depending what system
you're looking at and has a powerful
query language and then you can just
take all that - and so ingest large
amounts of data processes and produce
pretty high quality data
and information as with - I think that's
kind of really unique is that you have
two labels and you have the query
language Boardman was the or is the
monitoring system that monitors Google's
Borg what is prometheus
why do Prometheus get created so
Prometheus was started off in Sound Lab
by Julius enmesh and because when I
understanding they had stats t and it
wasn't scaling particularly well for
them so they started to you know doing a
spike to develop a better system and
that's where community started I did I
got involved like a year and a half
later and here we are now was it three
and a half years in so kind of just
started off as reaction to existing
monitoring systems not being good enough
right so Prometheus improves the
visibility into the internal health of
our services
what is Prometheus doing in contrast to
other monitoring tools welcome to a
specific tool in mind because there's
three or four broad categories no I
didn't have anything in mind what what
would be the most salient contrast in
your mind okay so I think the big one
you see is between metrics and logs and
then the other one is between metrics
and logs slash profiling and in all of
those in black box so start with just
talking about logs such as if you're
using the elk stack or fluent e or one
of those solutions so logs and metrics
are looking at the same data but looking
at it in a different way so if you have
a log line being produced per user
request for example then you know you'll
have zones so many fields in that log
entry but you're practically speaking
can't be limited to maybe 50 or 100 just
in terms of bandwidth and this resources
so for every single request you guess
you know these 50 things but you can't
really go to a thousand there just
because it was use too much disk Spanish
too much network i/o for metrics by
contrast they don't know about every
single event because their time
compressed so like every 10 seconds
every 20 seconds every minute you take a
snapshot
and because it's not looking at every
single request has been aggregated
across the time domain then you can have
10,000 of those no problem but you're
losing that per request information so
that's kind of where the big contrast is
and the way I would see it is that you
would start off with your metric system
like Prometheus and kind of drill down
and figure out which subsystems at fault
you know look at they don't follow the
latency true you're microservices
architecture and say okay it's this
service and looking at the rest of the
metrics because they've got 10,000 of
them
you notice okay it looks like it's say
the building subsystem and now that I
know it's in the bidding subsystem and I
know which requests pass hit them I jump
over some logs see who's been talking
about and getting snowberries and figure
out that oh it's this particular user is
this request and go from there so
there's this interplay then that metrics
kind of narrow down what's going on and
then you can jump to logs to get more
information to figure out okay we are
which subsystem now which exact requests
are the problem and that's where I see
the interpolate error and the other one
then is profiling so profiling I would
consider an team like gdb or if you're
putting a test race or any of the actual
profiling tools anything D Tracy where
you it's similar to logs and metrics
except it's doing both of them for a
really short period of time because it's
too expensive to do otherwise because if
you're sampling every microsecond or a
hundred microseconds and pulling in
every single event that is a tremendous
amount of data and you can't turn that
on all the time because it's too
expensive however once you've narrow
down the problem you can pull out your
profile tools to bug the problem and go
okay I figured it out I'm going to turn
this off now because I can't leave it
all all the time okay and so one of
those things that you listed there is
that you want to be monitoring services
rather than machines what what do you
mean by that statement okay so as I
mentioned the previous example there if
I have a machine that's running my
sequel in the old model of monitoring
machines don't have a check - you know -
my sequels turned on I'll have a check -
you know to see if you use okay the
memories okay but if that's part of say
a set of real replicas
for my sequel I no longer care about
individual my sequel machine I only
cared that Durer enough my seat was
running to provide good service so I
might look let's assume different
sequels being used extremely simply I
just might look and say right
what's the CPU load is it ok is the
latency ok across the entire fleet
and if two of them are down but all the
other metrics are fine like everyone's
getting good good service good
reliability then there's no reason to
alert so it's kind of not thinking about
each individual machine but thinking
about the overall service and the
overall view that the end user is
getting so it's kind of like the pets
versus cattle of you great so let's
start to talk about Prometheus in
practice what's a Prometheus client so
there are the Prometheus client
libraries there's in 11 languages I
think and the thing is in order to get
the most benefit out of the metric
system just like a long system you need
to instrument your code and what we
provide for these are the client
libraries so go peyten Java Ruby or the
main ones and you go into your code and
say right every time I pass this line of
code increment this team by one or every
time that I go into this function time
how long it takes and track stash then
that's all kept in memory and in a
memory stage and every now and then per
me just comes and takes a snapshot of -
so at its core it's just a way how you
say hey this is the interesting
information that I would like to expose
and we take care of all the bookkeeping
concurrency efficiency and all that sort
of thing for you so with the example of
maybe the ads platform that you worked
on what kinds of calls would a
Prometheus client need to implement what
methods wouldn't need to implement what
would it need to be able to respond to
and what kinds of information would a
Prometheus client need to produce so the
client itself is very generic so we've
got four types to counter to gauge to
summary and histogram and so a gauge
might be in progress requests because
that goes up and down like a gauge in
your car so that obviously goes very
high you
or maybe you've got a queue how big is
the Q versus the limit of the queue hey
Dan but counters like counting how many
requests are coming in how many requests
are coming in for different ad formats
like say flash versus text and the
summaries and histograms are for timing
latency or maybe the number of bytes per
request to track that over time and see
what that distribution is so that's at
the library level what the sort of
mapping you have for the types to us
provided but at the end of the day is
the user of the user two buildings on
top of - because the library doesn't
know anything about ads for example
right and what would be the process for
setting up that client what kinds of
programming hooks do you have to write
to set up those different metrics that
you want to give off okay so normally
what you would do so if I take the
example of the PI compliant you'd
install it by a pip - pip install
Prometheus underscore client isn't it
yeah and then you import it shows you
what the name of the piping you create
your metric so you'd go my metric equals
summary give us a name give it a help
string and then let's say wants to time
of function you're just decorators
so ask my metric time and that's it so
there's only really two lines of code
there one to set up the metric and then
one to use this great and then what is a
Prometheus server so Prometheus server
is the core part of religious issues
squash goes and talks to all the clients
and all the exporters pulls in all the
data stores it on local disk
preferably SSD and it runs rules on it
for a nursing and sends a flirts and
it's also available for graphing
requests or pulling out the data over
HTTP deep which is how almost all the
dashboarding solutions work do you need
a Prometheus server for each of the
different services that you want to
monitor yeah you could have one
Prometheus server
I had just nothing stopping you from
doing - Ruiz is actually surprisingly
efficient a single one can take care
like Asian or thousand samples per
second and but normally what happens is
that for organizational reasons each
team would get their own previous but
there's nothing stopping you running
everything inside one what are those
organizational reasons
for having won Prometheus server per
team for team uh well if two teams are
fighting over which way it should be
done that have different opinions you
can do - or you know they're different
resources and direct you know managing
is argument who's going to do which they
might have the room for media server
there's also an aspect of isolation
there if one team happens to put out a
metric that's way too big and starts
causing problems it's going to take
effect everyone else in that prometheus
server so just being able to say look
each of you have your own is one way of
looking at that and Prometheus itself is
also extremely easy to run it's a
standard UNIX daemon you mentioned that
different clients different Prometheus
clients might implement their metrics in
different ways are there also subjective
decisions to setting up the Prometheus
server yes there's lots of subjective
decisions and the main one comes up
around service discovery and what we
call relabeling so if you look at any
two organizations and how do you think
about their machines
maybe one's an Amazon ones in bare metal
so the one on Amazon cares about
availability zones and regions the one
on Behrman in bare metal only thinks
about data centers so they do have two
very different models of the world and
then the way that they'll think about
the targets and the key value pairs they
will associate with them is going to be
different and the interesting thing is
that turns out not only is this vastly
different between companies to the
extent that no two of them are likely to
have the same mental model it's also
very commonly different between teams
and even was in a team in the company
just because different people have
different ideas of production versus
development versus canary versus you
know people right lying stuff out by
customer or maybe you're laying it out
by team just that sort of subjectivity
comes in and to how you lating is out
because one of the advantages prometheus
is that everyone running drone for
meteor server can do their own thing and
model the world and way to make sense to
them how does it per media server
discover the clients that it wants to
connect to so for a service discovery
der is a few options we'd like support
ec2 Azure and Google compute engine I
think is still in code review and we so
we can just discover
machines videos and then you have
marathon and kubernetes
that we can pull that from there
including all the metadata they can give
us and then you've got a few things just
nerves and server sets on top a
zookeeper it's also console as well for
people to use it so those are more
generic certain explicitly does things
it's just designed for service discovery
so those are all there we can go out
fetch those and end user can model data
whoever they like on top of us using
relabeling once the service discovery
process has taken place what is the
communication pattern between the
Prometheus server and the Prometheus
client so the Prometheus server will
send out an HTTP request that might be a
CPS and it'll say this send me a scrape
normally to slash metrics endpoint and
the prettiest client will then send back
the metrics and I believe we and then
it'll just keep that issue each
connection open and keep on sending
normal HTTP requests at a regular
interval what is a typical interval it
depends the default is 15 seconds you've
got people going from sub second up to
several minutes what might be the
determination for how long you would
want to wait before pinging your
Prometheus client well if what was done
at the end of the day to resources
because you can imagine if you consider
one second versus 60 seconds that's 60
times resources you have to spend in
terms of network CPU disk and so on and
you have to balance those costs because
at the end of the day this is a
real-time streaming processing system
and those have costs so the Prometheus
server gets set up you've got a client
running but the client is usually an
instance of a replicated service
so let's disambiguate that how does the
communication between the server and all
of the different instances of a given
client how does that work like am i
doing a round-robin pinging of the
different clients or am i paying them
all at the same time house records
networks so it's independent completely
so we service discovery produces a whole
panel targets and let's say we're
working on
second interval and then the identity of
that target is hashed so he spread the
load around and then just scrapes based
on that so one might be at one second
one every seven seconds if you were to
and they're just that offset
continuously okay if you had many many
hosts it has just happened more and more
often than the space in those 10 seconds
be more filled or scrapes but each is a
go routine under independent just put a
hash for consistency how does the data
from the different instances get
aggregated so by default Prometheus will
just take in the data and there's
basically two ways to do the aggregation
so one is when you send your request
from say Gravano for graphing you hadn't
have an aggregator in Deer like some -
well on the fly do the math the other
option because you know if you get to
start touching a few thousand time
series that can start to get a little
expensive is from ETS can run rules we
call recording rules other systems call
them standing rules or standing queries
that it can just evaluate regularly and
pre aggregate that stuff so that's
cheaper to access because Daniel is
touched one time series rather than
thousands so it's the data being pushed
from each client or it sounds like this
central server is pulling data from the
clients yes Prometheus is a bull based
system so it's just pulling every 10
seconds say why is there such a debate
around the pole based versus push based
monitoring I'm not really sure I have
some ideas why it is a bit of a
religious issue the mid of the VIN
versus Emacs in like my own opinion like
there's not too much difference so
technical level between them like I
think pull is slightly better but only
very slightly one of the things that I
think may impact it is that Nagios is a
full system which you know it can be
tricky to scale and people are thinking
oh my guess is poor and I guess doesn't
scale therefore pull this and scale
which is an elemental fallacy whereas in
reality push and pull will both scale
pretty well so that's one thing that
might come into it another one is a lot
of the SAS vendors pretty much have to
use push for network reasons so if I
enter - but I really don't understand
release vehement opinions - at push or
pull can't scale because it is possible
to scale a boat just as long as you're
willing to spend time can you talk a
little bit about how the scalability of
a push based system contrasts with that
of a pull based system yeah sure so for
a push based system you are going to get
a stream of samples that are normally
gonna hit some form of load balancer you
then need to have something which is
going to take in those samples shard
them back out so we can you know hash
them across a set of servers and then
process them from there so the load
balancer there's normal ratings just
might be a little more challenging
because you have what might be a
tremendous volume of data always more in
place on a pull based system you don't
need that load balancer because each
particular per media server or other
pull system is already pre sharded shall
we say so you might have one for my
sequel say and it just pulls in that
data so you don't have an RDC difference
of having to manage all of that data
talking more about Prometheus when we
get data from a Prometheus client into
the Prometheus server how does that data
look what is the data format well there
is two data formats and the ones that
most users would see at which all the
clients produce is in text so there is a
few comments for metadata and then you
know be my metric tree or my metric 1.5
and it can also be labels in curly
braces inside there add the other format
which is equivalent is protocol buffers
at the moment only the go client
produces - and in fact the media server
and client use content negotiation to
figure out which one to use but the
format is the most people would end up
using is a simple text-based format and
you can produce this assuming you don't
need the escaping pretty easily the
volume of data from monitoring is quite
voluminous where does the data gets
stored does it get stored directly on
the Prometheus server or does the server
push it to some other database so the
data ends up stored on the community
server we recommend SSD for performance
reasons and in fact within
garbage encoding it's only one point to
tree bikes per sample in production use
cases and it sits there but we see
Prometheus isn't itself intended as a
long-term data store because the problem
wish you know a really long term data
store is that implies a distributed
storage system and that means the
distributed system and those are really
really hard to get right and you know
it's not my opinion that you want that
sort of higher distributed system
problem which is as likely to lock up in
an emergency as help you on you know
tightly coupled to tricky a server so
the thing idea is that we will have long
term storage of some form that for me is
use will push the data cache like today
you can push out to influx graphite and
open csdb
but is there still experimental support
ultimately we want to be able to plug
out to other systems they can do that
can store the data long term and they
can then medias and also transpire to
request data back from them and then we
have that decoupling where paradius will
have maybe a few weeks or months of that
or right there so even if the long-term
storage is having a little bit of a
problem you can still get your critical
monitoring in an emergency so is that to
say that the data on the Prometheus
server is not replicated it's somewhat
vulnerable to being lost yeah yes that's
correct
we generally considered premedia staff
to be ephemeral this it's a cache more
than anything else okay but in terms of
reliability if you want to hire high
availability and have you know not be
reliant on a single machine where
Prometheus it's really easy with a pull
model you just turn up a second premedia
server that's acting identifiy to the
first floor and then any both of the
data center both alerting all right but
I guess that's that replication model
would still potentially be vulnerable to
two diffs between the two but again I
guess this is a since its monitoring
you're not too concerned if there's a
slight difference in one instance of a
metric well yeah the thing is that there
are so many race conditions in
monitoring - this one doesn't actually
matter right
because like a tree oak imagine to
scrape or even you have the exact same
in a push based system is the network's
slightly slower or faster or the
scheduler and the kernels slightly off
you'll get slightly different results
and most of the races are of that
magnitude and you'll be looking at the
similar for this and as well if you
think about it you don't know what's
going to last example the ten seconds
scrape interval you don't know where it
is not ten seconds and if if you get
different answers and it's significant
to you in terms of alerting exactly
where you land in that ten seconds then
you're monitoring isn't going to be very
resilient to robust so you just need to
be able to resilient to that anyway
because that's just the nature of
monitoring so one thing I'm hearing here
is that the monitoring data needs
doesn't need to be as durable as
business data and this is you know seems
like a pretty fundamental difference
between how we look at business data
versus how we look at monitoring data
are there any other ways in which that
implication affects the architecture of
Prometheus well I wouldn't say so much
it's not so much durability as D
engineering trade-offs because
Prometheus we'd value availability over
consistency because at the end of the
day if your networks falling apart you
don't want a you know something like
zookeeper that's also going to fall
apart to depend on in terms of other
places for reliability so for example
between Prometheus and unit managers the
alert manager takes in all the alerts
because all of the alerting objects
inside Prometheus it generates alerts
and they go through that manager the
alert manager and talks to email talks
to pages usually talks to slack talks
the HipChat
can talk out Jason the HTTP if you
wanted to and our approach for making
that communication reliable is that per
media server is just continuously
repeating those messages and similarly
on the alert manager side there is a
repeat interval and plus if you retries
such that even because humans sometimes
dropped pages and ignore them by
accident or sleeping in or whatnot so
does repeat into both just say hey after
like an hour just resend that alert
because nothing's happened here so it's
just multiple retries all through the
system just to make
if things nice and reliable Russian
practice you know because of let's say
dumb machine crashes are washed you
might be missing your alert for a minute
but you'll get a minute later and that's
okay because it takes a human five
minutes deaths or a laptop anyway so one
thing you mentioned there is that you
know why one reason for avoiding
zookeeper and a system like zookeeper or
console they're often useful for
coordinating a distributed system by
providing consensus what are the
downsides of requiring consensus
coordination and how do you why do you
why can you avoid consensus when using
prometheus okay so it says this is great
when you need to consistency like you
can imagine for billing - is probably
the best example where you need
everything to be perfect and it's just
in monitoring we've made the for
community as we've made the engineering
choice not to use consensus not to use
at least highly consistent consensus and
because the problem is if you have a
quorum for example let's say your
standard example you need tree nodes for
corn and you were never partition that
knocks out one of them and you know
machine failure knocks out the other
suddenly you can't progress and if you
depending on exactly how you were set up
you could just then be dead in your
water and the monitoring system no
longer works whereas for me it's just
side steps all those questions by having
each server complete the isolation doing
its own thing is the consensus that
would be required in billing system who
are doing billing system instead of
monitoring would it be the point of
consensus around the information that is
being stored or I guess you you I guess
you basically would need you would need
multiple records whereas in this case
you just have a single monitoring server
you have a single Prometheus server that
is the monitoring sort that you're
looking at is the monitoring source of
truth and you don't have strong
guarantees about the consistency of that
data yeah well if you're really care
about reliability running to community
of servers which might have slightly
different data
right but they will provide you with
reliable emerging because just two of
them right so let's talk a little bit
about the Quarian model what is the API
for querying the Prometheus server yep
so the priority one is just HTTP API and
that you just send it a query and it
will send you back to results that's how
basically all the graphical solutions
work let's do so as you just say this at
this time execute this query or between
these time intervals at this off these
like at every 10 seconds give me the
results so what would be an example
query that we might make against our
monitoring data okay so a simple one is
you have a request counter let's just
say it's called requests underscore
total which is a little ambiguous so the
first thing you'd want to do is convert
dash into a race so a per second value
because a counter that's just
continually going up you know up into
the right just watch your watch in your
graphs but not that useful
so you as go at race requests total open
square brackets 1 minute closed square
bracket and close paren and then that
will just tell you 2 per second creation
for graph that but then that's going to
be per instance and we care about
service level stats so we want to get
rid of that instance distinguish
distinguishing those so we could then do
on top of - some without instance ratio
of requests total over 5 minutes and
then we have the request straight across
you know that metric for the entire
community of server and what you know is
a more general monitoring question but
what does an engineer like what are the
different situations where an engineer's
querying the monitoring server in the
day-to-day workflow am I only querying
it to set up dashboards am i querying it
to figure out a situation during a fire
what are the different reasons why I
might query my monitoring server so
normally you'd use it via pre-existing
dashboards because you know the key
statistics like requests per second
errors
see CPU usage memory they're going to be
an advanced board already for you and
but as you go down and debug into a
problem like you might have one per
service and then a few for the major
subsystems of that service once you
drill down far enough in it's possible
that there is no dashboard for what you
want already and you were just dando
directly start to write queries and
anything like that where you're
exploring a metrics maybe you're looking
about the code in one hand and knowing
hey there's this metric here that if
it's being incremented it means we're
going down this code patters will help
me debug and there's no dashboard for us
let me write a quick query and that's
sort of interpolated and it's like oh
right now we're going back code path and
say oh this metric and I'm just bouncing
between code and ad hoc queries right so
maybe an ad hoc query in the example of
the advertising is you don't have a
dashboard built to look at the metrics
of a individual website that's making
requests for ads but if you you know if
you start to have some kind of problem
associated with that website you might
want to create an ad hoc query and query
all the instances of that website
requesting an ad yeah yeah - because
this is an interplay as well you might
even have discovered this websites
because it's mesh missions an error
message in the log and it's just like
all these different tools are
complementary between your logs your
metrics your source code and you look at
all of them when looking at an outage
right so is Prometheus am I using it as
my logging or am I am I do I notice a
problematic a metric with my Prometheus
metrics and then I might go into the
logs on the Associated server and so
normally the previous with spot that out
so fermius is good for spotting mostly
systemic issues because you know you
notice that hey this error ratio is now
at 1% or 2% and then you'd always
noticed that okay I've looked at all the
servers this one server is 20% the rest
have none now it's time to look at that
server and see what's wrong and you can
drill down like that and then you know
guys server maybe look at logs from the
other side it's possible because for me
this is good for systemic issues if
you want to catch like a one-off thing
logs are a better option so what happens
with a network partition so in it when
there's a network partition between the
Prometheus server and the clients that
it's supposed to be pulling from and
that this partition lasts for an
extended period of time does that data
just get lost or does it get is there
some way to retrieve it so in that case
the data would just be lost and because
of the scrape it will happen
radius will attempt to scrape it'll
timeout in a reports the up variable is
0 and that's it and the question then is
like exactly whether you have h a set up
and one is on one side traditional one
is on the other could they like resync
and merge back in and the problem with
dash is just first question of semantics
because that's basically a Byzantine
scenario and you don't know which is the
truth the second problem is you just had
an outage or in the middle of an ongoing
network flakiness and you're just
chugging along your normal pace if
you're gonna start back filling data you
might be doubling your note or tripling
your load which might make any outage
worse so you've kind of got those two
problems there that you know does the
semantics it's not clear what the right
semantics are and this could actually
make an outage worse and it's that sort
of situation where by and large it's not
worth risking the reliability of the
system in terms of that average load and
you said in terms of the code and all
the risks there than just saying you
know we're gonna have a blip once a
quarter when I racks which you know with
someone brushes against this and that's
okay
I'm making that sort of engineering
trade-off realizing that you know
simpler is better
are there certain high sensitivity
services where that's not an acceptable
strategy there probably are but in that
case you're looking for a different sort
of monitoring I see because at that
point you are looking you're looking for
consistency over everything else and
then that sort of situation you would
turn off the service if the monitoring
broke which just because it would be bad
for you to continue accepting queries
because you can't reliably persistent so
if I had an architecture that had some
high sensitivity service where I need
really consistent monitoring
how would I make how would I fit in that
heterogeneity with a platform that is
mostly mostly find with using prometheus
like how does Prometheus how is probably
is compatible with that kind of
monitoring heterogeneity it probably
depends on the exact circumstances
you're looking at yeah because the
Prometheus if their choice is between
consistency and availability will always
choose availability because we're okay
with a small blip in Dasha if you're not
okay with a small dip in Dasha well we
can monitor the system that's doing that
and tell you how it's generally
performing and with all the metrics but
for that exact precision you'll need
some other solution so for example human
health data it will be a bad idea to put
that in Prometheus however there are
companies who are monitoring the systems
that are doing - and that's okay can
Prometheus monitor its own health oh yes
it's pretty normal to have for me -
scraping itself so do you say what's the
architecture to look like for that do
you have a separate server that is set
up to be the Prometheus server server
yeah that would generally be a good idea
it's normal also have each for me he's
scraping itself okay interesting
so what's the onboarding process like
for a company that wants to use
Prometheus well normally it's easy -
best start it's small - no risk so you
take the node exporter which is nice you
would know that Jess it's sir machine
agent you would install that on some
machines and install for me keys to
monitor doze and then you'll get five
six hundred stats ad from the Linux
kernel like your file systems your CPU
your network your disks and you can look
at that see if you like it get used to
the data model and from there expand out
maybe it's more infrastructure stuff
like so you Cassandra and my sequel
poster as a che proxy and Dan was a
really cool fool we can start getting
the real value which is from your
starting direct instrumentation and
using those client libraries in your
code obviously going straight to client
libraries has been a big ask because
it's saying hey I want my developers to
write a whole pile of code on this
system we're trying out which is
obviously a bit of a hard sell but if
you can say hey
the node exporter you can be up running
inside 20 minutes and it's easy to turn
off again not a big risk one person can
do is that's so much easier sell what
are the kinds of services that might be
more difficult to monitor with
Prometheus or might take more of a
complex architecture than we've defined
so far and so ones that can be tricky is
where there's lots and lots of
short-lived processes so Prometheus
generally presumes that things live for
a while you know let's say tens of
scrape intervals whatever that is so
things are shorter than that you're
going to miss things so there are some
things out there I think spark is one of
them - it has it's also very shortly of
things like even up pure service
architecture will be tricky although God
presents its own challenges other than
that anything where you are trying to do
what really looks more like blogging
then metrics is going to be challenging
just because of the cardinality of the
data because prometheus you know it's
worked on metrics and if you're creating
a new time series every time you run a
job and eventually that's going to run
into a performance notion what kind of
tools do people use in conjunction with
Prometheus so the most common one is
Ravana which is what we recommend for
graphing it's probably the biggest one
and not resonator tools are particularly
consistent across the user base and so
very so your company robust perception
offers Prometheus consulting what are
the typical situations that your clients
are in when they come to you and so
companies big and small so the smaller
company they might not have much
monitoring at all and just want a hand
getting things up and running and the
larger companies they you know have tend
to have an existing monitoring system
the tend to have an existing monitoring
team and they're just finding the things
you know they aren't scaling too well
it's a lot of operational averages not a
lot of value things aren't aligned and
it's like how do we best use for me
here's how do we deploy it how do you
make sure it scales are there any
pitfalls that we can avoid that sort of
thing yeah and these companies that
already
have some monitoring setup how do they
integrate Prometheus into the rest of
their monitoring infrastructure well
typically it starts off with Prometheus
as any new monetary system coming in is
just like a more advised rating there on
the side and and over time it starts to
get an emersion role as well and just
you end up then with two monitoring
systems for a while until you can cut
all over but it really is a question of
what your processes are and how you deal
with whether it's coming from a new
system when dashboards in a new system
like a lot of companies like most some
already is in Gravano so it's easy for
them to use the new dashboards the
challenge normally comes around more
around alerting and what that processes
so for example if you're used to using
something like you Chihuahuan sensu I
saw one pane at last there and then
Prometheus has a different one that you
need to sing about how you integrate
those together like deer rice a
consolidator or do you just have two
ones to look after or maybe you have a
completely different operation along
sure
so what aspects of an organization might
change once prometheus is running so one
of the things is because you can now
alerts on service level metrics that are
related to your resumes that you agree
with your customers that you can turn
off a lot of alerts from waking people
up in the middle of the night that are
directly related to - so that means you
don't need to have humans in rooms
looking at monitors and me raise your an
emergency you can scale that back and
reinvest that effort instead into
general engineering interesting how does
the work flow of an on-call person or
maybe an SRE change with Prometheus and
I don't think the workflow would change
too much it might have links to more
useful dashboards was going to richer
set of metrics depending on what system
you're looking at I think the process is
mostly the same because once your own
call was incident management okay do you
have any knowledge for how to what
degree prometheus is a rewrite of
Borgman
and in what ways is it different from
well public details around board one
there are too many of them there's a
vision
every book and someone's ramen
presentations so I'm not going to
speculate you okay fair enough
what's in the future for the Prometheus
project so the main Tings were kind of
looking at the moment and there's the
long storm storage is mentioned we want
to get that in there this is a big user
request we're also looking at making D
an irk manager highly available because
right now it's taking me a single point
of failure so we're looking at and
eventually consistent approach for - so
that it will continue to work in narrow
partition so if those are kind of the
two big things and and there's just
generally continuous improvement of
improved client libraries more exporters
more features information yes and so on
but those debate two things can you talk
a little bit more about the alerting
system we didn't discuss alerts very
much alerting is closely correlated or
closely related to monitoring but you
could talk about alerting and what the
unique requirements of a alerting system
around Prometheus are yeah so in
Prometheus labels are one of the key
aspects and the labels propagate all the
way through so you can reach alerts
based on labels so normally the idea
would be that you would have an alert
manager per company you know and or a
cluster of a northbounders per company
and one shared global configuration
which means the different Prometheus
servers can send alerts to other teams
you can imagine if I am say the
infrastructure Cassandra service I can
say hey you're running out of Kota or
whatever might - and and then you
basically have a tree that's walsh and
different people can say okay this is my
secret service they like to go to slack
and page or duty oh and this over here
is the cassandra service actually
they're using HipChat and are using op
and you can route like bash the
other big thing is that we have proofing
so a single nurse comes in it results in
one notification to page duty they could
also have us that you could say that if
this frees up the Machine down worst
because you still need someone to go fix
that and that you can have that come in
as a single notification even four
hundred machines died so that's a
massively reduces a number of
notifications so you can imagine your
page or Dan isn't it jumping around on
the table for five minutes as its
processing those but instead you get
silver notifications
hey there's 100 machines and that means
that you're not less likely to be
overloaded an emergency and the better
idea is what's going on but I need you
to see what's going on the other
advantages you can do this anyway so you
can imagine something like machines you
probably want to aggregated per data
center but let's say you had some system
that was replicating data globally and
you had the data is staying alert you
could aggregate that by alert name
because the chances are like if the
upstream data provider is having a
problem that all the data centers are
going to alert us at the same time so
you can consolidate it down to one
notification I'm getting closer to the
idea of one notification per booth calls
which is kind of nice the other thing
the art manager has that's you kind of
need is silences so in advance of a
maintenance you can just put in some
labels and say hey if it matches these
don't do silence don't alert for the
next two hours so that's really useful
as you expand out and somewhere
interesting aspects of their manager is
this performance because when you have
labels and metrics it's easy to create
many many alerts so you need to make
sure that's pretty highly performant so
you could easily have tens of thousands
of the nurse active at a single time
great okay well Brian I think this is a
reasonable place to stop where can
people find out more about you and your
work
sure and well the main place look at
would be robust perception website in
particular into blogs there so I write a
post usually on Prometheus once a week
and as well for free medias generally
Prometheus that IO has everything what
kinds of things have you written about
recently and I looked a bit more about
why we don't have one agent per machine
the robber and exporter per ting I have
looked at monitoring for consensus have
looked into how counters worked it's
written so many posts at this point it's
hard to keep them all in inline well
that's great okay cool that's a good
reason for people to go check out your
blog well Brian I want to thank you for
coming on the show and talking about
Prometheus in detail I really appreciate
it thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SC -
radio now to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on Twitter at SC
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Applause]
you
[Music]